A Guide to the Pendleton Family Papers 1830-1929
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Pendleton Family Papers 1830-1929
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
415
This collection consists of ca. 1000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift of Mrs. William H. Forrest, Pavilion VIII, East Lawn, University of Virginia, on 30 March 1939.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 1000 items (3.5 Hollinger boxes and 5 oversize ledgers; 2 linear shelf feet) 1830-1929, papers and memorabilia of the Pendleton family, mainly the financial records of Dr. Eugene B. Pendleton of Cuckoo, Virginia.
Dr. Pendleton (born 1851) attended medical school at the University of Virginia during the academic year 1868-1869, but completed his M.D. degree at the University of Maryland and then settled in Cuckoo with his wife, Bettie B. Pendleton. Their daughter, Anne Meredith Pendleton (born 5 August 1895), married William Mentzel Forrest (born 19 October 1868) on 21 June 1932. Forrest taught Biblical history and literature at the University of Virginia from 1906-1938 and lived in Pavilion VIII on the East Lawn at the University during the years 1935-1938. Included in this collection is correspondence and related material regarding Bible examinations given in Virginia high schools which Forrest graded for the State Board of Education.
The major part of this collection is comprised of bills, receipts, accounts, bankbooks and checkstubs from Eugene Pendleton's financial records. He acted as financial agent or attoreny-in-fact for Ann F. Pendleton (Mrs. L.S. Pendleton) and many of these financial papers are records of his dealings on her behalf. Also included is a small section of financial letters and papers of Sallie Anne Pendleton, Beattie Pendleton's mother, which date from 1830-1889. A few of Dr. Pendleton's financial letters, a draft will of Susan Ellen Meredith, whose executor was Eugene Pendleton, and assorted memorabilia and printed material can also be found in the collection.
Ten bound volumes complete the collection. Five of these are Dr. Pendleton's ledgers dating from 1887 to 1925. He appears to have run some kind of store or business in addition to his medical practice. Ledger no. 4 contains a draft of Sallie Pendleton's will. The oversize volumes are mostly photograph albums containing pictures taken at the Columbian Exposition and in Mexico, Italy, and North Africa. The fifth volume is an undated commonplace book containing Bible passages, notes on British history and illustrations of national and family insignia.
Arrangement
A small section of correspondence, legal papers and personal papers is followed by the bills and receipts, bankbooks and checkstubs which comprise the major portion of the collection. These are divided between those relating to Sallie A. Pendleton, Eugene B. Pendleton and Ann. F. Pendleton. The financial records are followed by memorabilia and printed material. The bound volumes and oversize bound volumes are listed at the end of this guide. Each section is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Letters to Sallie Anne Pendleton 1830-1889 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Eugene B. Pendleton 1878 July-1929 Feb (Box 1)
- Correspondence and related materials re William M. Forrest's course in Bible study 1929 Feb-May (Box 1)
- Correspondence Fragments n.d. (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Legal Papers 1930-1917 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Personal Papers 1874, n.d. (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Accounts of Sallie Anne Pendleton 1839-1889, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts, and Accounts of Eugene B. Pendleton 1884 Apr-1925 Mar, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts and Accounts of Ann F. Pendleton 1911 Jun-1914 Jul (Box 1)
- Bill, Receipts and Accounts of Ann F. Pendleton 1914 Sep-1926 Apr, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Checkstubs and Bankbooks 1907-1922, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Memorabilia and Printed Material n.d. (Box 2)
- Bound Volumes
  - Ledger 1887-1911, w/index, ca. 500 pp. (Box 3)
  - Ledger 1889-1897, w/index, ca. 700 pp. (Box 3)
  - Ledger 1889-1905, w/partial index, ca. 330 pp. (Box 3)
  - Ledger 1890-1920, 1925, w/index, ca. 200 pp. (Box 4)
  - Ledger 1891-1901, ca. 100 pp. (Box 4)
  - Commonplace Book n.d., ca. 70 pp.
  - Photograph Album (Chicage World's Fair, Italy) n.d., ca. 70 pp.
  - Photograph Album (Mexico, North Africa) n.d., ca. 70 pp.
  - Photograph Album n.d., ca. 45 pp.
  - Photograph Album (North Africa) n.d., ca. 45 pp.